RUBIERE RAMIREZ

Geospatial Specialist | Spatial Data Engineer

rubiere.ramirez@gmail.com (+501) 636-5355



github.com/rubi3r3



SUMMARY

A geospatial specialist and a spatial data engineer with over six years of experience in proprietary geographic information systems (GIS), free and open-source GIS, spatial data programming, spatial database management, remote sensing, earth observation and spatial data engineering.

EXPERIENCE

Geographic Information Systems Assistant,

Statistical Institute of Belize

■ September 2022 – Present

Q Belmopan, Belize

Administer and maintain Enterprise GIS, spatial databases, services, Web GIS applications and perform earth observation on the built environment.

- Create, administer and maintain spatial databases on PostgreSQL database with PostGIS extension.
- Create, administer and maintain web applications on free and opensource software for geospatial (FOSS4G): GeoServer & Mapstore2; and on commercial off-the-self (COTS) software: Portal for ArcGIS & ArcGIS Server.
- Create Sentinel-2 Geomedian of Belize with Google Earth Engine and classify urban areas with machine learning in Python.
- Create tools to automate tasks and to standardize the extraction, transformation and loading of non-spatial data and spatial data into SIB's spatial data repositories with SQL, R, and Python.

______ Geographic Information Systems Technician,

Statistical Institute of Belize

July 2018 – September 2022 **Q** Belmopan, Belize

Create spatial data using front-end geospatial software and produce maps.

- Heads-up digitized building footprints for the entire country of Belize.
- Perform remote sensing techniques to detect changes in urban areas in OGIS.
- Process aerial photos from drone imagery in QGIS and ArcGIS Pro.

Geographic Information Systems Technician,

Coastal Zone Management Authority and Institute of Belize

Assist CZMAI with data creation and field data collection.

- Heads-up digitized and updated building footprints for Caye Caulker using Google Earth Pro and existing building footprints.
- Assisted with the collection of land use and building information in Caye Caulker using Open Data Kit for android devices.

EDUCATION

B.Sc. in Natural Resource Management

University of Belize

mathred 2012 - 2014

Pelmopan, Belize

SKILLS

R | R-Spatial | Python | GeoPython | SQL | Spatial SQL | QGIS | ArcGIS Pro | Geographic Data Science | Data Engineering | Remote Sensing | Earth Observation | PostgreSQL PostGIS | FOSS4G GeoServer | Geovisualization and Geocommunication | Web GIS

ACHIEVEMENTS

Enterprise GIS in FOSS4G

Developed and implemented Enterprise GIS infrastructure with free open-source software geospatial: QGIS and PostgreSQL Database with PostGIS extension.

Web GIS in FOSS4G

Deployed and maintained Open-Source GeoServer and Mapstore2 with Apache Tomcat on Apache HTTP Server on SIB's GIS Servers.

Web GIS Development: Full-**Stack PERN Application**

GIS Web Application for Census Progress Tracking

Geovisualized census progress coverage by creating a web application using open standards: Mapstore2 web created using GeoServer, PostgreSQL database with PostGIS extension and ETL process automated with R programming.

Created {rvr2spatial}

A package in R programming designed to facilitate the ETL process from MariaDB to PostgreSQL PostGIS.



Built and maintained PostgreSQL, Express, React, Node.js geoportal to geovisualize the Statistical Institute of Belize's spatial data.